hello and welcome to a new and ancient
story
this is a podcast a series of
conversations interviews
and occasionally speeches dedicated
to the transformation of self and
society the basic idea
is that we are moving from a story of
separation to
a new story new for the dominant culture
at least
of inter-being what that means will
become apparent
as you listen to this series we explore
things like technology
spirituality agriculture healing
economics politics ecology relationships
education i mean pretty much
everything that is undergoing a
transition today
as our old story nears
collapse if you want to engage these
ideas more deeply
you can come to our website
charleseisenstein.net
everybody charles eisenstein here with
my friend daniel schmachtenberger i
would
call him a non-institutional and
non-institutionalized intellectual i
find that
the most interesting generally speaking
the most interesting intellectuals and
philosophers
tend to be outside of academia these
days
maybe there are some exceptions but i
feel like yeah
like daniel's a kindred spirit because
both of us
have walked a path
that wasn't prescribed and
it's taken us both to places that were
not on the map
at least that's that's how daniel has
landed on me
that he's gained insights and developed
perspectives
that are not on the menu
conventionally speaking so yeah i'm
really excited to
share some of those with you we just
recorded
a podcast a couple days ago for his
podcast
and um dan you were such a
gracious and generous and skillful
interviewer
i felt uh really humbled by that and i
hope to be able to return the favor
so welcome to a new ancient story thanks
charles it's fun being here with you i'm
looking forward to
us getting to have this dialogue yeah
maybe we could begin
by i'll just say that you use
certain vocabulary that is unfamiliar
and it took me a little while listening
to you to really begin to
understand what you were saying um
talking about things like
multi-polar traps and existential crises
and
and there's a few uh non-rivalrous games
things like that
and i think that those will come up and
when they do come up maybe we'll
pause for explanation of those things we
had a plan to start about
talking about the paper clip maximizer
problem and this like it's like this ai
thing
but it has huge implications for the
direction of
civilization even down to a deep
philosophical level so
is it cool if we just start with that do
you want to introduce that yeah yeah
yeah
so um some of the listeners have
probably heard of the paperclip
maximizer thought experiment for those
who haven't to construct it briefly
i believe the term was first introduced
or at least introduced to the public by
a researcher named nick bostrom in a
book called super intelligence
where he was exploring the risks of
artificial intelligence and there are
many different
ai risk scenarios and one of the general
ones is
called a paperclip maximizer and the
idea is that we don't need
an ai getting a sadistic will of its own
against us or even being applied to
weapons to be problematic
the idea of the paperclip maximizer is
you basically
have some goal that you want to train an
artificial intelligence system on to
help
optimize whatever that goal is and you
know when we look at being able to train
an ai
on a particular goal like winning chess
or winning alphago or something like
that we see that
if they understand the boundaries of how
they could optimize that they get
capable of things that humans couldn't
do very quickly
and so let's say i have a factory and i
produce whatever
and in this case just for simplicity and
selena's sake i produce paper clips
and i train the ai system
on the goal of maximizing the number of
paper clips that i can produce
and increasing the efficiency of my
paper clip production
so first it gets trained on the data
sets of my entire supply chain
and my whole manufacturing process and
it sees where there are inefficiencies
in the manufacturing in the supply chain
it figures out how to tighten up those
those inefficiencies and the business is
just running better that's awesome that
could even seem like a good thing for
the environment because of decreased
inefficiencies and things like that but
if it continues to get more and more
intelligent and
actually as it gets more intelligent it
gets better at getting more intelligent
the key to the paperclip maximizer is
that it does two things it does whatever
goal you train it on plus it gets better
at its ability to do that goal
and it gets better with an exponential
curve because as it gets smarter
it's also smarter at figuring out how to
get smarter so you have compounding
returns on intelligence
that are then all applied to doing
whatever the thing is so
um pretty soon it starts running out of
substrate
to make paper clips and so it starts
uh looking at how to make paper clips
from additional substrate so it's starts
realizing it can use recycled metals not
just whatever the original metal was and
trash and whatever and of course then it
eventually runs out of that
and eventually it needs to use the stuff
that humans need
uh to live for substrate and then
eventually needs to use the humans and
then it turns the whole universe into
paper clips
and the idea is that if you had
something that is
way more intelligent than us in terms of
its just strategic capacity to
achieve a specified objective it's a
very narrow kind of intelligence we're
talking about right now
in terms of we're not saying that it's
good at defining what is meaningful
but if outcome has been defined and it
has access to
the data set of things that are
connected to that outcome it can do
optimization
better than we can and as we try to
learn how to deal with it it's going to
learn how to deal with us faster than
we're going to learn how to deal with it
right so the
chess systems competing against human
systems are getting better at beating us
faster than we're getting better at
learning what they do to adapt
and so we're getting more and more
obsolete as chess players on a very fast
curve
well this is what we're already applying
ai to do
like before we start to think about true
general ai and
we are already across many industries
applying artificial intelligence to
optimize fairly narrow metrics and you
know classic
example is facebook or social media of
any kind
google whatever but we'll take facebook
as a simple example
uh trying to optimize the goal of time
spent on site
how much time does a person spend on
site because the more time on site means
the more advertising revenue and at the
end of the day it's a for-profit company
that makes money and
returns to shareholders by advertising
revenue that's proportional to time on
site
but it's there's an ai running it's
optimization
of what makes my news feed as sticky as
possible and what makes the
notifications
as engaging as possible to come back so
it finds out that there are certain
things and this is the same as the
youtube
suggested views feed finds out that
there are certain things that i'm
particularly
more likely to pay attention to and it
optimizes for those now it's not
conscious it doesn't care this is just
pure analytics
but it's effective and so we'll see that
my news feed is totally different than
your news feed
and it's based on what is the most
sticky addictive stuff for me possible
and it tends to be that if i get
it's probably going to be things that
involve attractive people of the
opposite gender
and things that scare me anger me or
create and group out group dynamics
because it's appealing to my limbic
breaks it was appealing to my rational
brain rationing i'd say i need to get
the fog off facebook and go get some
work done
and so we see that just using facebook
as an example here
people who are on the left and people
who are on the right of a political
spectrum
have been shown to increase the
radicalization of their view
because from using facebook not because
facebook has the goal to make them
radical but it simply has the goal to
engage them more and the stuff that
scares them and makes them angry
and that they share because they're
scared and angry is stickier
and ends up being more viral so we're
like oh wow the paperclip maximizer of
facebook
or of youtube videos that is simply
trying to maximize time on site
has as an externality the entire
sense-making capacity of the world
getting ruined right like and
uh individual lives getting worse in
quality and relationships getting more
messed up and changing social dynamics
right
that's that's a big deal so we can see
that paper clip maximizing is already
happening with
what we call machine learning artificial
intelligence
and the thing that charles and i
have discussed previously and i think
we'll get into now is that
the idea of a paperclip maximizer in
artificial intelligence
it's a thought experiment for the risks
of artificial intelligence but it's also
then
a thought experiment for how our
civilization as a whole works
independent of artificial intelligence
which is if you have a
some kind of system of intelligence that
optimizes a particular goal maybe at the
expense of other goals right because it
has a very particular goal
and it gets better at doing that there
are problems associated with that if
it's part of a complex system or those
other things that it might
harm to optimize something matter for
the continuance of
life and thriving and so we've talked
about
what we call civilization as a whole in
modern terms and we can think of
capitalism to start
but it's not just capitalism it's
capitalism as the center of kind of
in group out group competing against
each other in a rivalrous way
game dynamics of which capitalism is
kind of at the center but
nationalism and all forms of power
structures are
there's it's a kind of collective
intelligence
not an artificial intelligence but a
collective intelligence that predisposes
what all the humans do
and it gets smarter and better at doing
what it does
and it happens to be reductive meaning
moving things in the direction of
particular simple metrics
and so i'll kind of take a break and see
charles where
you want to go before building out the
example but the
idea is that civilization as a whole
right now has paper clip maximizing
elements as a collective intelligence
system that is
the core of the issue that we have to
address
yeah it brings up for me lewis mumford
and his characterization of the mega
machine he called it
yeah which basically he was saying what
was the first machine
in the sense of of a industrial entity
and he said it was it was the first
builder civilizations
where human beings were the components
of this machine
doing standardized jobs controlled
by the hierarch by the pharaoh or
whoever it was and this allowed whoever
was in control of this machine
to perform god-like feats
which was why the pharaoh or whoever was
given a
semi-divine status and he says the basic
model of the machine
already existed 5000 years ago yeah in
the standardization of roles and then
what happened is eventually the human
parts
were replaced by mechanical parts so
that
one person now controlling a machine can
perform god-like feats like
moving at rapid rates of speed flying
through the air communicating
instantaneously over vast distances and
so forth we're all gods
now because we are at the helm of
of a machine and so like so the the
machine
of civilization could also be thought of
as a computer
or as an artificial intelligence because
it definitely has an intelligence beyond
that of any human being it can solve
problems
that no one person could solve and so
then
then it's what you're saying is okay so
what are the
imperatives of of this machine
and gosh it sure looks like maximizing
gdp
or maximizing human dominion or
producing more and more you know more
stuff or
whatever motives and incentives are
built into the machine it's doing
a better and better job at accomplishing
those
and yeah where is this going and how can
we
stop the world from turning into paper
clips or money
right so let's let's explore the
model applied to civilization in some
detail
so if you think about a colony of ants
or termites you see that the colony as a
whole has
certain kinds of intelligence that the
individual ants don't have right
none of the ants on their own know how
to make a
ant mound of that type or underground
labyrinth of that type and yet the
coordinated behavior
of all of them has the capacity to do
that so we would call this a collective
intelligence
and it rather than being centralized
that there is one consciousness
of the uh ant colony controlling
everything it's a decentralized emergent
collective intelligence
where we generally think of it and we
can see
many examples of that so the thing that
we're describing here today is that the
the thing that we call civilization is a
collective intelligence
that is misfit
for its ongoing continuation with itself
misfit for its ongoing continuation with
life it has kind of mathematically
self-terminating processes built
in and we're getting close enough to the
self-termination points that those can
start to become
eminent so we'll we'll look at those so
for instance
let's just take capitalism to begin with
and we'll expand because we're not going
to say that communism wasn't this it was
too capitalism was just the better
version which is why i got selected for
um so if we look at
what capitalism is as a system of
decentralized incentive
the incentive is controlling or
influencing patterns of human behavior
if people can make money and survive
doing a particular thing and they make
less money
and are less able to survive doing other
things then there is a incentive to do
certain things
and if they can move beyond just
surviving to actually getting ahead
there's more incentive to do the things
that keep increasing their
capacity because of all the things that
money makes possible
and eventually those who are near the
top of the money hierarchy
want to continue to double down on
whatever it is that increases
the capacity to be there so then you
look at
what the nature of incentive
fiscal incentive looks like and we say
okay well
i can't really get dollars for
leaving whales live in the ocean it's
not i can't convert their light
life onto my balance sheet but if i kill
them i can get dollars for that
by selling the whale meat and i can't
get many dollars
by leaving trees alive in an ecosystem
but as two by fours i can sell
them so in general there's a movement
towards extraction and commodification
okay so we see the nature of that
movement we see that
maybe the largest block of global
economics writ large if we were to
take all the things that make it up is
the military industrial complex so we
see that war is super profitable and i
can make a lot of money by doing that
we look at all the areas we see so money
ends up being a
decentralized incentive system that
orients everyone towards the things that
can make more of it
and as we look at the evolution of kind
of the economic system itself we say
just like the paperclip maximizer gets
better and better at being able to do
its thing we say okay well
original humans were just sharing
resources in tribal settings and then
there was exchange between
tribes and then we can look at uh
early currencies and then eventually
fiat currencies and then fractional
reserve banking and then high speed
trading on digital
fractional reserve banking that's very
much like the curve of a paperclip
maximizer
that is getting better and better at
being able to get all of the humans to
do its bidding and here's kind of the
key
way of thinking about it it doesn't have
its own ability to be an actuator to do
stuff in the world
outside of getting humans to do the
stuff and
so any human that does the bidding of
capitalism
meaning converts more of nature into
stuff
that can be put on a balance sheet and
we're oversimplifying here but
to get the idea we'll expand in a moment
anyone who does its bidding well
will get more power within the system
right they get more money which ends up
meeting more influence and then also
more influence to continue to double
down on their ability to keep having
that influence i get enough money and i
can actually start to make laws
by paying lobbyists that support the
government's ability to have me keep
making that money or to even subsidize
how i make the money or
i make enough money that i can start
controlling the media
to be able to control the collective
opinion of all the other humans to
support me continue to make money so
there's this
uh as i do better in the system i get
more capable of doing more better in the
system
so exactly it's exactly parallel to the
ai learning how to learn
better and better right and the humans
so the humans that basically do the
bidding of the system get more power in
it the people who are at the top
of the power hierarchy are the people
who are
uh most perfectly aligned with
the will of that system and then you
look at kind of what the will of that
system not from a
anthropomorphic but just from a
behavioral disposition point of view
is and then the people who
oppose the system if they're actually
effective at opposing the system or a
risk to those who are in power and they
will inherently have less power so they
get taken out
of some form and if you look at like
famous people who got assassinated
throughout history
they were pretty much all against the
paperclip maximizer and they mostly got
taken out by people who were stewards of
the paperclip maximizer at the time the
power
system and so the interesting thing is
it's not like
the pharaoh or the head of the big banks
or the whatever is
actually in charge the key thing is that
they are
a symptom of a system that incentivizes
people to do those behaviors
they are actually an emergent property
so it's like
are there sociopaths running the world
yes of course there are sociopaths
running the world
um because if you create a system where
to get to the top of a power hierarchy
you have to beat lots of people in zero
sum win lose games to
get up i have to actually be good at
beating people at
good at and oriented to beating people
at zero sum win-lose games
to get to the top which will include
lying and disinformation
and externalizing harm and layoffs
whatever it has to
involve but you see it we have a system
that attracts
sociopathy and then conditions rewards
and trains it
and whereas like living in a tribe you
would not do well as a sociopath
right you'd do very badly and so you
don't have an evolutionary environment
we have a system where
the very top of the power hierarchy is
an evolutionary niche for those who are
most abusive with power
in those particular kinds of ways but
effectively abusive meaning that they
they figure out how to game the system
to support them continuing to do it
um so it's like the are there sociopaths
around the world of course
are there people who conspire against
for their own goals against other people
of course there are and for every
watergate or enron there's a thousand
that don't get publicly acknowledged
that doesn't mean every conspiracy
theory is true most of them are
gibberish but
a lot of them are true but that's not
the cause of the problems it is a
symptom of a system that incentivizes
conspiring
if you incentivize something it will
happen right that's kind of the supply
and demand
dynamic of it and at the heart of the
supply and demand dynamic
is not a particular good or service it's
get more power within the system
yeah so sociopathic traits are
basically part of the job description
for being in the elite
and if you don't enact those traits then
you will be squeezed out in one way or
another
and somebody who's more sociopathic will
step into those rules
and you're also saying that there are
conspiracies but the whole system itself
isn't a conspiracy it's not that an evil
elite
created this system and is running it in
order to enslave everybody it's that
the system created the evil elite that
operates its levers so they're more
like functionaries than puppet masters
well and then of course it's recursive
right that's how the system works it's
the deep learning system has a recursive
element so the people who get into the
positions of power will then
work to control or to influence public
opinion and
influence law to support them being in
power
so do they do stuff that is directly
harmful to the system writ lars or to
the commons at least
yes of course they do and do they do
stuff that increases their ability to
keep doing that
of course that is what the system
predisposition is
well that's not very cheerful daniel
i mean it seems like like and they're
getting better and better and better at
it or are they
like some of these things they get
exponentially better for a while but
then they
you know level off and they reach an
inherent limit like it looks like our
civilization is
doing that in a way which is reflected
in
the slowdown in the rate of economic
growth
um the decreasing effectiveness of our
technologies to
solve basic problems like it doesn't
look so exponential anymore
what do you think about that yeah so
if we think about the
development of uh the things we call
civilizations historically
there will be some pioneering effort to
go explore some new
territory niche of some kind
most of those don't work and they're
expensive and then the ones that do work
become the basis of
a new development and then you get a lot
of development on whatever that thing is
hey now we're mining like we figured
that thing out or
now we've got this spot that's good or
now we're working the plow here or
whatever it is
and then you will start to get to a
place where you get um
you know early people having captured
much of the
power system associated with those
things the
pioneering landscape having not having
open opportunities for new people to
pioneer from scratch
and so then everybody else has to work
for the people who already
did the early pioneering in some kind of
way
and so the first people who were doing
whatever the
thing was had a direct relationship
with pioneering innovation with actually
the natural world itself
or with um yeah reality itself
and then and so they were able to get
ahead through an innovative process
at a certain point there's no more space
to actually
innovate or come up with new stuff
so on your own so what you end up doing
is working for the existing system and
now
all those people are in a domestication
system and there is an upper limit on
what they can do and the only way they
can get ahead is to climb
that power hierarchy so they go to work
for a company rather than the very few
people who found the company
and of course most the companies fail
and the founders
do it they fail the few that make it and
there's now a huge cash room coming in
then everybody goes to work there
the people who work there are not going
to have as much power as the people who
founded it
as time goes on it gets bigger even less
so and
at a certain point climbing that power
hierarchy whether it's a government
or a corporation or whatever becomes my
only way to get ahead more than doing
fundamental
innovation and so i have to get better
and better at figuring out how to
win at power hierarchy kinds of stuff
and so if you look at
the court of versailles and louis xiv
and the courtier type dynamics there was
a world where everyone like nobody was
trying to make
fundamentally new stuff or new
innovation there was no real pioneering
space
everyone was just trying to get more of
the power somebody already had
uh you know bestowed on them and this is
what we call politics
and the things that give you power
within an institution are not
necessarily the same things that
make the institution more effective make
the government work better make the
corporation make more money even
like so very very often
uh actually it's usually the opposite of
that right so
we we can't do things that are so
damaging to it that i
damage my ability to get ahead but i
also don't need to optimize the
organization i have to optimize my own
bonus structure within the organization
i have to also optimize my ability to
get away with the fact that optimizing
my bonus structure
is not optimizing the company and so
that looks like
hiding transparency like systems that
decrease transparency and the decrease
accountability so we'll make a limited
liability
law that doesn't make me accountable to
certain things we'll make
certain kinds of corporate veils where
nobody can even tell who's doing certain
things well
you know whatever right and those
basically those breakdowns
of accountability and justice end up
leading to again doubling down on the
environmental niche we're doing
the more sociopathic thing actually is
selected for
but i guess why i'm saying this is we
see this interesting thing where
you know in the last years and decades
there's a tremendous amount of new
wealth
that is not part of kind of older wealth
systems because of a proliferation of
software tech
and the people who do that are still
part of the paperclip maximizer
as a whole but of a slightly different
type
someone who didn't come from the mindset
of being at the top of a power
hierarchy and mostly maintain their
power hierarchy without actually
innovating new novel goods or services
or
discovering new stuff basically that
adaptive environment
is pretty close to purely political
which is mostly sociopathic environment
the
make new tech from scratch that can meet
some good or service that can meet some
need for someone is actually a more
adaptive thing so we can see
that happening which is cool we can then
also see though that that tech
even if it was created for an a positive
intention at first
both has externalities like facebook
created
hope like will be generous and say for
the purpose of connecting people
socially
actually leading to much more social
connectivity and political polarization
radicalization and
breakdown of sense making writ large and
that's because of its financial
structure
if it wasn't optimizing for ad revenue
it wouldn't have to optimize for time on
site it could apply
its capability to radically different
things right
and the same is true with youtube's
algorithms the same is true with
all of these so even if it starts for a
positive purpose it ends up becoming
captured by the machine if it is to
continue to be successful within this
larger machine of
capitalism okay so there's
two things that i want to basically name
that you've already
described and just want to make them
explicit and see
how they relate one of them is this
i call it a mega machine but
civilization that's getting better and
better
at converting the world into money on
the other hand
we have inefficiencies and dysfunctions
within the machine that are
incentivizing
behavior that doesn't necessarily make
the machine get better and better
at converting the world to money because
what serves
someone's personal interest you can
actually make the whether it's the
corporation or the mega machine
as a whole less efficient so
does this mean that there is
a light at the end of the tunnel like a
way out
from a bleak future of the entire world
gets turned into paper clips
like could we build an alternative or
could we somehow take advantage
of the built-in inefficiencies
of organizations as we know them that
are
financially motivated to supplant the
civilization with something better
is there a solution yes i
propose so and we'll get to it um
it's not from exploiting the
inefficiencies because what makes a
corporation inefficient or a country
inefficient
actually still serves the paper clip
maximize or writ large because it just
moves the center of power from that
corporation
from you know microsoft to google from
us to china or you know british empire
to us or whatever it is and so
the paper clip maximizer keeps doing
quite well as the local parts rise and
then collapse rise and then collapse but
continue to whenever one part is
uh starting to collapse all the adaptive
things that learn just move to a new
center
there's a couple more ideas we have to
construct to get into the alternative
because we
we haven't specified the key of why this
system works the way it does yet
okay i'll be patient
so one thing you know you and i've
uh talked about this before when we to
define what evolution is
not just in a biologic sense but the
deepest sense that complexity
science gives us is that evolution is a
increase in ordered complexity
that leads in the direction of emergent
properties
and that what's being selected for
emergent properties so
you know a cell respirates
even though none of the molecules on
their own that make up a cell respirate
it's an emergent property and so there
is advantage to those molecules being
together from even a thermodynamic
perspective
that there isn't being a part so we can
say that biologic evolution is a special
case of this larger principle by which
subatomic particles come into
atoms into molecules and there is a
process of increasing complexity but
specifically
complexity that doesn't have emergent
property doesn't get selected for
so it's ordered complexity in a certain
way as emergent property the emergent
properties come from synergies
and so we can say evolution is defined
by these kinds of
synergies and increasing complexity so
we look at a biosphere
and we see we see the complexity of a
single organism like a cell that is
really incomprehensible and or a tree
but then we look at the
intercomplexities of all the cells
in a tree or all the cells in an animal
and then the relationships between the
aerobic and the anaerobic bacteria
between the predator and the prey in
between the
gas exchanges and all the things like
wow right
and and it keeps increasing over time
of course you're going to have some
species die off and new species come
about but we're
over time you get an increase in the
complexity of the species from
single cell you know up to neurologies
and
then reptiles and mammals and primates
and on and on
right more complex nervous systems more
complex behavioral patterns
so the interesting thing there is we can
we can see
the paper clip maximizer has the exact
opposite
directional orientation as evolution
does
evolution is increasing the orderly
complexity
and in
which automatically means that it
increases the type of diversities in the
system
and the synergies between those
diversities right so in an old growth
forest
there's radical diversity and also
radical synergy across
all those diversities and and it's
oriented to the continuation of both
the diversity and the order the agency
and the communion the individuality and
the interconnectedness
um and the paperclip maximizer takes
complex stuff and makes simple stuff out
of it
and so if we think about that for a
minute we
take the example of a tree in the forest
tree in the forest is super complex
you know if we ask like what is the
value of a tree we have to start by even
saying value to whom
and whose perspective who is the
beneficiary of value
and we start to look and we're like well
pretty much everybody
is a beneficiary of the value of the
tree but they're different kinds of
value the
pollinators come get a certain thing and
the birds that live in it get another
thing and the squirrels that live in it
get another thing and the
fish that live in the river that is
cleaner water because the
top soil was stabilized by the roots get
another thing and the fungus in the
soil that has the mycorrhizae that has a
relationship with the roots is another
thing we're like okay and the
sequestering of co2 and the production
of oxygen for the mammals
so the tree has a a kind of indefinite
number of beneficiaries
that it benefits with an indefinite
number of different outputs
right so this is like not optimizing for
a single output
to a single kind of beneficiary it's uh
you can't even call it optimizing
actually um but if you wanted to say
that just
loosely here it's optimizing for
synergetic
benefit across this whole interconnected
web of things
and so we take the tree and it's not
worth anything economically to me but if
i cut it down
and turn it into a two by four now it's
worth something economically
and the tree
is self-organizing and self-healing
if i burn the forest the forest will
regrow right
if i burn the house that i'm in made of
two by fours it doesn't regrow if i burn
the two by four it doesn't regrow
and so i take something that is
anti-fragile
that is resilient and i turn it into
something non-resilient and fragile i
take something that affects many
beneficiaries and i try to capture it
for one beneficiary
i take something with many value types
and i try to turn it into one value type
right so now i turn this very complex
thing of a tree into a very simple thing
called a two by four
and then i might build a complicated
thing out of the simple things a house
complicated different than complex the
tree self-organizes the house doesn't
self-organize
make a blueprint somebody builds it from
the outside the forest self heals the
house doesn't self heal
the forest evolves towards more
increasing complexity the house and
tropically breaks down in time
yeah so humans build complicated stuff
complicated stuff is inherently fragile
our our laptops don't self-repair they
don't self-organize neither do our roads
or
infrastructure or water systems or
whatever and so
we convert the anti-fragile complexity
of the natural world that evolution
brought about
into simple and then complicated
fragile in entropic more than syntropic
stuff which require top-down management
because they don't organically maintain
themselves
right i mean maybe another example of it
would be the
imposition of monocultures cultural
agricultural various kinds of
monocultures on the world
which is reduction of uniqueness and
complexity into something
simple the ultimate of which would be
the monoculture called money
which is pure quantity right so say i
take the tree
i turn it into two by fours and now i
can accumulate a bunch of these two by
fours
so i can build something out of it but i
can also trade them
but they're a little bit cumbersome to
trade actually i can't the liquidity is
not high enough that i can just trade a
bunch of them in a hurry if i want
something else
so i actually don't even want to store
the two by fours i want to sell them
right away and get
money because even though the money has
no actual value it's purely
representative value meaning i can't
build a house out of it or eat it or
really anything because of its liquidity
for other forms of value it seems to
maximize my
choice my freedom my optionality so
i don't want trees i want two by fours
and i don't want two by fours i want
dollars
and then because i can't spend a dollar
on amazon i actually don't want dollars
i want bits
which is the digital dollar in an
account that has maximum liquidity and
its potential
and so we actually see each of those are
a step towards more simplicity
and so now we have a world that wants to
convert
the natural world and human creativity
and human labor and all of it
into bits of a particular type that are
abstractable
fungible tradable optimizable
that is exactly the opposite direction
of evolution it is decreasing orderly
complexity it is converting
the anti-fragile natural world into an
increasingly fragile built world
and then we're trying to run
exponentially more flow through an
increasingly fragile system so when we
look at
oil pipeline spills we look at the
fragility of the system that's trying to
run more and more stuff through it when
we look at wars and economic collapse
and environmental collapse we're looking
at breakdowns of fragile systems
but if we keep trying to convert the
anti-fragility of the natural world
into increasingly fragile world that
we're trying to run exponentially more
flux through
that self-terminates and process
self-terminates
but there the fiscal incentive is in
that direction
and again it doesn't take everyone like
you could have a lot of people who are
like
man something matters more than money i
don't want to do that but anyone does
that thing
and of course they might have a
fiduciary responsibility to shareholders
they might
whatever it is anyone does the thing
that continues in that direction
and they gain so much more money which
equals power which means adaptive
advantage that
everyone else has to justify continuing
to do that or they lose in the economic
competition by default
now that's the concept you mentioned
earlier called the multipolar trap
the multipolar trap is one term to be
able to explain a scenario where
you've got a lot of different agents
that are in an assumed competitive
relationship with each other so the
agent could just be individual people
competing with other people or it could
be tribes competing against each other
or corporations or
countries right but some agent that is
acting for its own
benefits through the polls in the
multi-polar right
okay and
so if any of the agents does something
that is bad for the whole
bad for the commons over the long term
but that provides
a lot of near-term advantage to them
there's a big incentive for them to do
that and
if they do then all the other agents in
the system
have to try and do that as well to not
lose
where that agent was getting ahead
or they do lose by default so they
basically anyone
exploiting such an opportunity creates a
gradient for everyone else to race to
exploit that opportunity
so the tragedy of the commons and the
arms race are two classic examples
tragedy of the commons is okay
i don't want to fish all the fish out
because i actually think fish are
beautiful
i'm in a tribe or i love them i want
them to be there in the future
i don't want to cut down all the forests
i think forests are beautiful i want to
keep hunting in it
and i actually don't need that many
trees but if i
only cut down the trees that i need from
our traveling cuts on the trees we need
and to leave the forest the forest still
isn't going to get left because the
other tribe is going to go cut down the
trees
or some other tribe beyond that one is
so i don't even have the choice to
protect the forest
so if it's going to be them cut down the
trees or me cut down the trees and if
they cut them down
they're going to build weapons to attack
me they're going to build storage of
resource to get through the famines
they're going to all those things
i have to go cut the trees down not only
do i have to cut down more than i need
and store it i have to do it faster than
they do
because they are an assumed competitor
but they're thinking the same thing
they're only doing that because they
assume i'm going to
so everyone is now in the situation
where they assume somebody does the
up thing and i'm like well we
could make a treaty
okay so me and this other tribe and the
other tribe close by all make a treaty
that we only cut down x number of trees
cool but the other tribe is totally
sucks and they won't join the treaty and
so they're going to do the up
thing so we can't even keep the treaty
we all have to do the thing
right so then we cut down all the trees
and we actually race to go from
axes to saws to chainsaws to whatever to
cut down the trees as fast as possible
to get there before the other guy
and this is why 80 percent of the old
growth forests are gone this is why
ninety percent of the large fish species
uh populations are gone the whales or
whatever else is because
multiple traps so that's the tragedy of
the commons example
and the arms race is if some say
somebody produces this new terrible
weapon
and nobody wants to live in the world
without terrible weapon because it's
just worse for everybody
everybody's more likely to die in
terrible wars but if anyone produces a
new terrible weapon everybody else has
to produce a terrible weapon to be able
to have any chance in organs and plus
they have to produce defenses and
counter offenses to the terrible weapons
they have to increase
total terrible weaponry in a lot of ways
right and if they don't they're just
going to lose
so we saw that with nukes we see that
with ai weapons happening right now we
saw that with chemical weapons biologic
weapons we saw that from the cannon
right like just
the the bronze age the stone tools and
so here's how we define it
where an agent can get ahead independent
of the well-being of other agents
or the commons and even at the expense
of other agents of the commons
that's the rivalrous game theoretic
environment rivalrous meaning i am both
rivalrous with the commons and rivalries
with other agents
in that environment my ability to
exploit the commons
faster than the other guys and find some
new way to do it in which case then all
the other guys need to be racing to do
that same exploitation with me
there's no way to bind that
unless we try and create the
historically the only way to bind that
what we call multi-polar trap is with
some
agreement right that's what the um can
we make a treaty to not do it is but how
would we enforce that anyone keeps the
agreement well there has to then be some
monopoly of force that is stronger than
any of the agents that can say hey if
you don't keep the agreement we're going
to put some
force on you to push you back into it so
one of the main reasons we have created
states
governments is to bind multipolar traps
so you have some monopoly of force
meaning the police force that is backed
up by the national guard or the military
force
whatever that is backing up law because
law wouldn't be that thing without
monopoly of force
so the idea now is we try and create
laws to bind the multi-polar traps you
can't cut down trees
in the protected area right in the
national forest or whatever it is
so we have an epa or an fda or an ftc or
somebody to protect against some bad
action
backed up by a monopoly force now and
that's a national level or a state level
but it can also be at an international
level that's the idea of what the
u.n is right the that after world war
one
we're like oh national governments on
their own can't actually govern in a way
that keeps them from
wanting to blow the whole world up and
our technology is now so
terrible that we can't have wars like
this anymore so can we create some
supranational organization that was the
league of nations
league of nations obviously failed in
its goal of preventing world war ii
and so we changed the name called the
united nations and so the goal there was
let's
let's do nuclear disarmament because now
nuclear is the really big thing and
let's prevent
spread of nukes and the use of them and
we haven't had world war
iii formally kinetically yet but
we went from two countries having nukes
to
19 or however many having nukes and
nukes not even being the
concerning thing now in the
proliferation of
exponential tech mediated weapons
everybody's got them not even state
actors so we're like
okay well why is it that the top down
force the un
has a monopoly force why can't it keep
the nations
in check well because the nations have
too much power for the
u.n to have a monopoly of force over
them so say you're a country with nukes
and we're trying to do nuclear d
proliferation we say okay you're gonna
you're gonna give up your last nuke now
you're like no i'm not that's
stupid i give up my last nuke
and somebody's gonna come invade me
who has nukes and
so you'll lie and say this is your last
nuke we'll stockpiling some other ones
right and then not agree to the
inspections or whatever it is
um and because you assume that whoever
else is giving up their last nuke is
also lying
and stockpiling some and so this is the
multi-polar trap thing right
and so then if the u.n so nobody wants a
volunteer to give it up so
then can the u.n force and say we're
going to force you to give up your last
nuke they're like no off we have
nukes you're not
you can't do that so multipolar traps
from bottom up dynamics market
style dynamics can't be bound by the
market
um or countries competing by each other
can't be bound by the country they can't
be bound at their own level
and top-down forces can only bind them
when there is a monopoly of force and
that is oriented to bind them
and at this point because of exponential
tech
there can never be a monopoly of force
in the same way there was previously
um because the bottom-up forces are too
powerful
to be overread in that way and so we say
oh
all right so now we have this place
where we have multipolar traps of all
kinds right now it's
build ai as fast as you can for all
purposes that there's incentive for
including weapons
right or things like that and if anyone
makes a law
that tries to protect against
something like an environmental
destruction whoever has the economic
interest to do that environmental
destruction has the economic incentive
to pay lots of lobbyists
to change the law and to hide that under
some
other thing that doesn't seem to make
any sense that nobody pays attention to
and to pay for campaign budgets and to
you know all those types of things so we
end up seeing that
law falls to economic incentive when
it's even though it's supposed to bind
economic incentive the problems of it
because economics is actually deeper in
the stack of power
than law and government is
yeah quite a few things in there you're
basically establishing uh one pillar
after another after another
of an argument that i think you're going
to continue developing
i'll just add like maybe a supporting
comment i read a little bit about the
actual tragedy of the commons the
textbook example
was villagers grazing their sheep and
it's to the advantage of any one
villager to graze
them as much as possible so that his
herd increases but if everybody does
that then
the pastor gets overgrazed and
everybody's sheep die
but no it's to nobody's interest to rein
themselves in
historically however according to what i
read
that didn't happen because the community
had explicit and implicit agreements
social pressure if you were grazing too
many sheep then people would
make life difficult for you and you
would feel shame and so people actually
got along quite well and didn't destroy
their commons until
market economics and the idea of the
separate individual came in
and introduced that logic and weakened
the informal ways that people
regulated the use of the commons and
when that happened
then the imposition of force by a state
became necessary
so it was kind of a substitute for right
yeah okay so this is a super important
example
when we say that there's a top-down
force that binds the bottom up one that
has a monopoly of force
monopoly of force in the way we think
about it today is
um a actual police force or military
force
that is asymmetric to the physical
rebellion capacity of a
subset of the population now there was
something that you could think of as a
kind of monopoly
of influence before state type dynamics
that weren't just mediated by
those type of police forces and it was
what you're describing right in a
community
if someone starts to behave in a poor
way
being ostracized from the community
right like being shamed or being
excluded or people not wanting to
interact with you
you're you can no longer do it you can't
actually get ahead or survive if you
can't interact with people
and so uh that was actually able to work
at a fairly small number of total people
where there was transparency to the
dynamics
right so there's only three sheep
herders that can be letting that grazing
happen
and anyone who's doing the thing
everybody can see
so remember how he said when there is a
breakdown of transparency or a breakdown
of accountability you create the
environmental niche for the bad actor
so as we get to larger sizes everybody
can't see what everybody's doing and it
becomes easier and easier to obscure
this
which is then where you have to try and
say okay well can we make government
bodies that can do investigation and
that kind of thing so if you think about
like if i if i'm in a big
corporation nobody no one's really
watching what i'm doing
um in the same way that they would be in
a tribe and particularly the only other
people who will be watching that closely
might have
somewhat i can coordinate it that they
might have somewhat aligned interests
but it's not like the actual end users
that we're making products for that are
on the other side of the world have any
idea what i'm doing
and or there might be some
accountability within the corporation to
make sure you're not embezzling funds or
something like that
yeah that you know but that only keeps
you
acting in the interest of the
corporation not in the interests of
the other the other stakeholders
right and so this is actually really
important
for most of human history we had people
inside of families inside of extended
families inside of communities
inside of groups of communities and
there was
there was organization that happened at
each of those levels it's kind of like
cells inside of a tissue inside of
organs inside of organ systems inside of
a body it's not just like
50 trillion cells inside of your body
with no
substructured organization it wouldn't
work at all but right now
the family doesn't actually provision
resources all that much families become
largely broken saying especially the
extended family and the families were
actually very good at provisioning
resources
having an inner investedness in each
other that wasn't game theoretic
and knowing what each other needed
having enough awareness that if
someone had resources they could
provision within the family
and communities tribes were also pretty
good at those types of issues because
you could actually see what was going on
and they could be inter-invested in each
other
and now you mostly have the individual
interacting with the market in the state
right the big giant
everything that is impersonal and the
individual
as a voter consumer producer
and that system is
definitely broken
right so the problem isn't so much that
there are
too many people or that the scale of
society is too big it's more that there
aren't
enough coherent intermediary
structures like you can imagine having a
community where it's small enough that
people
mutually regulate each other's behavior
and you're not going to graze your sheep
too much because then the blacksmith
isn't going to help you and
and the herbalist won't treat your kids
and so and then you can imagine having
the community
interacting with other communities in a
similar way where if one community
doesn't behave well
then the other ones assuming that
they're interdependent enough the other
ones
don't provide it with something it needs
then you could have
groups of a community of groups of
communities
and then a community of a community of
groups of communities and you could
imagine a planet operating on that level
which would be
a complex organic structure
rather than a disintermediated world
where you have an undifferentiated mass
of people and a hierarchical control
structure
in the model of industry which is all
about the standardization of parts
the standardization of inputs and
outputs and so forth so
maybe is where you're going with this
like some kind of successor to the
industrial
model of organizing society
um so so let's look
at complex systems
that evolved and have
uh orientation towards increasing
evolution and anti-fragility and like
that
so there's a couple key principles that
we see that are important here
let's say we look at the 50 trillion
give or take cells in a body
which cells kind of run the show is a
silly question
there are no few cells that are elected
representatives or dictators or whatever
which cells have really asymmetric power
over all the other cells
there are and that was a delusion of of
of
physiologists i mean they people thought
that well the brain must be in charge
but it's totally not like yeah yeah
right
the cells in a petri dish will continue
to do their own thing
from liver cells or kidney cells or fat
cells or they are self-regulating in a
bottom-up way
there are top-down effects where the
neuroendocrine system is gathering
big picture messages and then
communicating big picture information
back for coordination but the
coordination is not just happening at a
bottom-up
cellular and top-down whole system level
there's coordination happening at the
level of a tissue
and there's coordination happening at
the level of an organ and that an organ
system so there is something that is
neither bottom up nor top down
and where the the bottom up influences
cascade all the way up to this emergent
top thing the top-down influences come
in turn affect the bottom-up ones
but it's happening at all these layers
and there's a kind of coherence
phenomena
and so this is neither market nor
government this is something
much much more interesting and much more
complex but you see that
at the level of a cell there's a
symmetry of power where all the cells
they're all doing their thing but none
of them have asymmetric power over any
of the other cells
and you can think about as far as
messaging goes cells are capable of
sharing messages to
other cells that they have a particular
relationship with mostly adjacent cells
right
we can see some effects where it'll be
an endocrine effect but it's still
going to be things of a particular
receptor type that it evolved to have
that relationship with
so why that is important let's say a
cell becomes a cancer cell this happens
all the time
to some degree just because of mutation
oxidation whatever that occurs the job
of the
body is that to prevent the kind of
carcinogenesis that makes cancer cells
to make it much less common but when it
does happen
to actually convert the cancer cells
back to healthy cells and if it can't
then it has to kill them so they don't
spread
uh kill the whole body because then
they're acting in a way where their own
interest is pit against the interest of
everything else unlike healthy cells
healthy cells you know liver cells are
not competing with kidney cells
to accumulate more of the scarce
resource
and liver and kidney writ large are not
competing in that way right the
bones will move calcium they're holding
into the blood for ph buffering or
into the brain for calcium ion dynamics
and then move them back in for storage
and
there's this very complex provisioning
that is optimizing the well-being of the
whole system across every kind of metric
um but imagine
that one cell became cancerous and it
had the ability to broadcast
its cancer signals its cancer genes to
every other cell simultaneously
and they would be uptaken because they
had they hit some kind of
addictive gradient or near-term
advantage gradient well
everybody would die of cancer very very
quickly
and so it's important that they're only
able to affect nearby ones and the
nearby ones exert a restorative force on
that one
and so it actually requires the cancer
is going to grow somewhat slowly the
body has a lot of opportunity to deal
with it this is the only reason we're
not all dying of cancer all the time
and so today though
when you look at what broadcast media is
or you look at
just asymmetric power of any kind well
what is the asymmetric
power of a putin or a trump in terms of
kinetic warfare compared to you or me
right it's it's trillions of times what
is the asymmetric
fiscal power of the gates or bezos
compared to us what is the
asymmetric messaging capacity of a top
celebrity right in comparison
and so we look at the tools that are
mediating that kind of asymmetry so
broadcast messaging is a good example
i can transmit a meme that will catch on
because
it has certain stickiness or limbic
hijack dynamics but it's actually a bad
meme it moves things in the wrong
direction but i can broadcast it to
everybody and there's no check
mechanisms to see that that was actually
a good meme that was adapted for the
whole
that's actually super destructive super
dangerous and you say
can we have anti-fragility in the
presence of
any agent becoming maladaptive and being
able to influence the whole
asymmetrically and
so now we come back to the example of if
i was in a
family in an extended family and a tribe
and a and i started doing something that
was maladaptive for the tribe there
would be a
pressure that sought to make me healthy
and first it would see it pretty early
and sought to make me healthier before i
had the ability to influence everything
um this is an important thing that's
missing and
so when we start to think about
extending asymmetric influence
technologies and where an individual or
a small group can influence the whole
thing too much which
exponential tech does exponential tech
means i have exponentially bigger
levers to make choices with i mean more
impact from my choice
but nothing ensuring exponentially
better choice making
and better in a good for the whole not
just a game theoretic get ahead at the
expense of everybody else choice making
that equation itself exponentially more
powerful choices without
exponentially better choices is also a
fundamental
problem right so we need to say how do
we get good choice making
to scale faster than the power of our
choice making
this this is like a fundamental thing
that we're looking at here
but so let's say we extend
exponential technologies the next
several years we say okay
so crispr biotech gene drives
making it to where more and more people
can do really up things on
smaller and smaller scales
the ability to do cyber warfare ai
nanotech whatever these types of things
because
as we see with exponential tech it
doesn't just make exponentially more
power
it also makes the power cheaper right we
look at the cost of computation
or any of these things which also means
then more decentralized so it's not only
state actors it's non-state actors it's
smaller and smaller groups having more
and more power
and that's like having each cell if it
mutates have the ability to affect the
whole system too
rapidly so there is no possibility for
anti-fragility for resilience
in that particular structure so if you
ask
people who study existential risk
like exponential tech immediate
existential risk how do we
avoid blowing ourselves up from stuff
that people are doing in their basement
with no exotic materials that
nobody can tell a very common answer
is ubiquitous surveillance
universal surveillance everywhere nobody
can be doing anything in there
and again we said it's when there's a
lack of transparency that a lot of these
problems start to happen
so that we can see why someone would say
that right is
we don't want somebody in their basement
being able to build crisper weapons
that's a bad idea
and yet we also don't want 1984 and
if we have a surveillance state where
the state is
there is a structure that guarantees
that the state is going to move towards
corruption because that's how top-down
power hierarchies work and you have
a power hierarchy of one-to-many power
structure the state has surveillance on
everybody everybody doesn't have an
input back to that and it's oriented to
be captured and corrupted
all right that's so that's a failed
system but not having that seems like a
failed system in the presence of
exponential text it's like what what the
do we do
so you know you can see that even with
the technology the killing technology
of in guns as opposed to
knives you just can't kill as many
people with a knife if you get if you go
wacky right so
when you look at mass shootings
whenever we hear that somebody took an
ar-15 and went and shot up a bunch of
people
and the news reporters go and do the
investigation
the neighbors all say yeah he was real
quiet he kept to himself we never heard
from him etc what that means is that
person might have been progressing
as a cancer cell right they might have
been progressing in their own
psychopathology depression
and upset for years with no one
actually engaging with them to be able
to see that they could go to the store
buy food and no one noticed
if they were upset or not or healthy or
not in the way that they would in a
tribal
dynamic if you have people who can
isolate themselves progress in their
psychopathology not be checked
and they have ar-15s you're going to
have those kind of shootings
if they have access to progress in those
types of isolated dynamics and they have
worse weapons it gets worse so what do
you do well you don't have to have
service
surveillance by the top down state
remember there's a top down force that
happens not at the level of the whole
body to a cell but even a tissue to a
cell
and so this is like if that person was
part of a family and part of a tribe
where they actually needed each other
they couldn't just use this abstraction
called money to get their needs met
without having to interact with humans
in any meaningful way
the other people would see hey this
person doesn't seem well let's
spend more time with them and work with
them and help them be healthier
so this is a kind of surveillance but
it's not a top-down captured
surveillance it's a mini to mini rather
than a one-to-many
kind of system so there's a symmetry in
it and this
is a how do we
have more awareness of what's going on
for everyone so that
we can help people actually be healthy
this is not
sufficient for but it's necessary for
having
choice making be our choice making basis
be capable of holding our choice making
power
yeah i've been thinking about this for a
long time
in phrasing a little bit differently but
but how do we restore community
when we have a system that strip minds
community
because community is based on it's not
just
people knowing each other but it's
people depending on each other
so the economy as we know it replaces
interdependency with dependency on
distant abstract institutions
and anonymous service providers mediated
by a very complicated division of labor
when production is on such a vast
scale and requires such a fine division
of labor
how can you have meaningful community
when all of our needs
our tangible needs at least are sourced
from afar
and not yeah so
right so so one one avenue is to
relocalize
and replace some of the functions that
we've handed over to
a global mega machine with locally met
needs
and there's already a movement in this
direction for example the food movement
people are wanting to source their
food locally but the economic system
is stacked against that because of
externalized costs
mostly so lettuce shipped from
california
to the east coast is cheaper than what
it's grown here
uh because of the subsidization the
preferred subsidies embodied in roads
for example
and the external environmental costs et
cetera et cetera et cetera so
from what you said the people who wield
power
aren't going to change those conditions
because they
are part of the paper clip maximizer i
mean they
are their job is to maintain those
conditions
from which they personally benefit but
also
the paper clip maximizer benefits in his
production of paper clips so
and it seems that the system has only
strengthened its grip
over the course of my lifetime and i
mean forever
so it looks like a really bleak picture
you're painting here
like yeah we know what the solution
would be to restore
to each other to place to community
so that we can have informal bottom-up
organic surveillance or you could say
transparency so that we
can identify the cancer cell before it
starts shooting its
cancer messages out to the entire world
before
one unabomber in his basement with a
you know genetic engineering crispr
technology is able to
unleash something horrible we know what
we have right now we have a
rivalrous system that compels everybody
in it
toward to enact behavior that is going
to destroy everything
and we know where we want to go which
would be to a society
organized much more like a body with
multiple levels
of complex structure interacting with
each other
and enabling us to be transparent
to the people around us in this kind of
nested system
that is non-hierarchical that has
uh an interplay of bottom bottom down
and
bottom up and top-down dynamics that
evolves toward greater and greater
complexity we know where we are
we know where we're going do you have
like at least like a little
uh a little through line from
here to there like how do we take a step
into this transition
the heart of the problem
is the word that you mentioned a couple
times is power
and what we're talking about is a system
where the primary concept
is not power power meaning power over or
power against
in a rivalrous way in a game theoretic
way
where the core idea is
resiliency we could think of we could
use different terms resiliency
strength whatever where the goal is not
to maximize my
power over the environment or other
agents it's to maximize my sovereignty
and my ability which includes my ability
to not be controlled by other agents
right to be anti-fragile to power
without actually engaging in the game of
power
it's a fundamentally different and kind
of critical distinction because the game
of power is actually the paperclip
maximizer
and capitalism is simply a part of it
and
this is the key thing for us to
construct so we can show what the
alternative looks like
a lot of people are going to maybe be
thinking um
daniel it seems like you missed biology
class and
don't understand how darwinian evolution
works and
that these type of rivalrous behaviors
are nature itself and we evolved to have
these kind of
rivalrous dynamics and you're asking for
something that is outside of human
nature
or outside of nature itself this is an
important point to address
because i can't offer what an
alternative is if people think that it
goes against
what is actually possible and something
that we
need to understand in terms of the
nature of this situation we're in is
that
if we look at ecosystem natural systems
came about through evolutionary process
there are rivalries dynamics there's
also heaps of symbiotic dynamics and
there's
a lot more symbiotic dynamics and there
are rivalrous ones
um but there are rivalrous ones and
they're worth pointing out
but even the rivalries dynamics end up
driving
symbiotic dynamics at a higher level and
this is a key part that we have to
understand and we have kind of
understood it we've based our theory of
markets on this idea
so you know the key example is we
look at competition in terms of uh
various animals of the same species
competing for reproductive opportunity
and obviously predator-prey
relationships being directly
wrist there's plenty of things that look
zero sum and so we
look at a fox chasing a rabbit
and if the rabbit if the fox catches the
rabbit the rabbit's dead
so that's pretty clearly rivalrous if
the rabbit gets away the fox might
actually starve to death or not be able
to feed its kids
so there's a very clearly rivalrous
dynamic
but we see that the foxes as a whole
species and the rabbits as a whole
species actually depend upon each other
they couldn't even really survive
without each other and they're driving
each other's evolution
because the slowest rabbits get eaten
the slowest foxes starve
and don't uh don't mate the fastest of
both get through
and then those genes reselect and so
rabbits are evolving and foxes are
evolving because of each other and if it
weren't for the rabbits the foxes would
have nothing to eat and if it wasn't for
the foxes the rabbits would eat
themselves to extinction
so we say oh this actually very
interesting at
one-on-one interactions there's a
rivalrist dynamic
but it leads to a macro symbiosis so how
is it that microrivalry becomes
macrosymbiosis
and the key insight there is that there
is a symmetry of
power between the fox and the rabbit
between the lion and the gazelle between
the shark and the tuna between
all these places where the prey gets
away as often as it gets caught
and or more often whatever the
particular symmetry is
but there is a there is actually a power
symmetry that has it to where that
dynamic between them
doesn't have one get asymmetrically
ahead of the other one so they both
co-evolve as a result of that process
but we could imagine if the foxes had a
mutation where they got a hundred times
faster in one generation
that they would eat all the rabbits
their population would boom and then
they'd all starve to death
so breaking the cemetery of power would
actually break how evolution works but
the symmetry of power is never broken in
evolution because
what leads to right natural selection
mutation
and then selection of the adaptive
mutations both survival selection
and sexual selection that happens the
same everywhere
right there is a distribution of what
creates the mutation dynamics and so
um there the cemetery of power is
maintained as the whole
system steps up
until technology came about and with
early humans homo habilis double down
and homo sapien
was the beginning of a creative process
that was different than anything that
had happened in the evolutionary process
up to that point
where we were able to increase our power
not
through the same kind of slow
mutation process that was increasing it
on all sides
in a way that actually broke the
symmetry of power so we could make stone
tools and we could go hunt and we became
radically more lethal became better
predators
faster than the environment could adapt
to our increased
predative capacity and so we could
overhunt a whole environment
and then not only did our tool making
capacity allow us to do that it also
allowed us to put on
a skin and move into an environment that
we hadn't adapted to
so we could go to the arctic like polar
bears in the savannah like cheetahs and
like we could go everywhere and become
the peak predator in every environment
that's a fundamentally different deal
because microrivalry leads to macro
symbiosis only if there's a power
symmetry if the power symmetry is broken
microrivalry leads to macro rivalry
without bind and ends up
self-terminating
and so if we take evolutionary rivalrous
dynamics and multiply them
by technology which creates increasing
asymmetry and essentially exponential
technology
you do get a unstable system an unstable
oscillator it eventually breaks down so
because
of our technology the the social
darwinist idea that markets are
basically a darwinian evolution
process where different companies will
create mutation on the same product and
the one that people like will get
selected via supply and demand dynamics
the idea actually doesn't hold in the
same way
because we do have the ability to
outstrip environments faster than they
can reproduce themselves
kill whole species whatever and if we
are debasing the substrate upon which we
depend
then we're self-terminating and that's
how this is happening so
our tool making has given us enough
power
that rivalrous dynamics are
unsustainable this is the key thing that
i'm wanting to share
rivalrous dynamics where they occur are
actually sustainable where there's a
symmetry of power
but we have a radical asymmetry between
humans and other humans
and between humans and the rest of the
ecosystem
in nature there's a symmetry between
lions and lions right the
in competing reproductive opportunity no
line is a thousand x more powerful than
another lion
and between the lions and the gazelles
right now we've broken it to where the
human to human and the human to nature
asymmetries are many orders of magnitude
so we have to figure out anti-rival risk
relationships with each other that can
hold that technological power with each
other
and with the ecosystem or we actually
self-terminate
and this is the key thing in the
presence of exponential tech
and even before exponential tech right
like we started desertification
thousands of years ago
we started extincting species a long
time ago or over hunting
environments and we also started larger
scale warfares than any
other animal was capable of having as
our technology got bigger
it's and so whole civilizations have
collapsed for these reasons it's just we
have a totally globalized civilization
for the first time
where the scope of this is much larger
the
degree of power we have necessitates an
evolutionary change
like a fundamental change to
evolutionary process itself where we
can't model ourselves as apex predators
anymore
where you know a great white shark can
kill one tuna at a time we can use an
a super troller with a mile long drift
net and kill all the tuna like
that you can't model yourself as an apex
predator with that kind of asymmetric
technological power
when you have the ability to destroy
whole ecosystems make whole new
environments genetically engineer
new new species you have to model
yourself as
nature itself which is the only thing
that has had that power previously and
recognize that
if we're moving in the direction of
increasing simplicity the paper clip
maximizer direction
that is a self-terminating direction if
nature is moving in the direction of
increasing orderly complexity and we're
powerful enough to affect all of nature
we have to actually be
stewards of the increasing orderly
complexity of the whole system
so we move to from just being parts of
the whole competing with each other with
broken power symmetries to saying okay
the level of power we have
we've kind of got the power of gods we
have to have the wisdom and love of gods
to be able to steward that that's a
way of thinking about the transition
where it is
unconscious evolution of the whole right
natural selection is kind of this
evolutionary process that we don't think
of as conscious
then tool making is a conscious process
but it's just parts
right in rivalrous relationship with
each other
the next part is conscious evolution of
the whole which is really this kind of
new
epoch phase and that is a fundamentally
different relationship to not only power
but even identity
and this is where you come to why we
need a new story and a new mythos where
where there is no way of thinking about
me
my race my nation independent of all the
other people and independent of the
ecosystem because i actually don't exist
without them i can't and my rivalrous
dynamics with them will lead to
their increased rivalrous dynamics lead
to the self-termination of the whole
so when you ask how does it transition i
don't know that we have the time to get
into
what is a new method of
collective sense making and collective
choice making and
provisioning of resources that replaces
what we think of as economics and
governance now
and how do we do tool-making in a way
that doesn't cause externality
but culture actually has to be the first
part of the transition
because our new social systems our new
economic systems are going to require
new types of tool-making that mediate
them in the same way that it's like you
can't do cryptocurrency as an economic
system without a computational
infrastructure for it
and you can't have stores of grain that
lead to capitalism
or that lead to private ownership in
that way before you have
plows there are tools that mediate the
new type of social agreements we're
going to have new methods of sense
making
largely because we also have new methods
of communication and
information processing and computational
infrastructure and whatever
but how to even build the tools that are
oriented to that as opposed to oriented
to some other purpose will be some
subsets of the population that have a
new story a new value system that then
build tools
that can be in service of that to then
build social systems
within people's participation with that
social system
recursively reconditions that underlying
value system
and it's a movement from separate
competitive self to
interconnected symbiotic self from us
as modeling ourselves as competing for
apex predator status to stewards of
the whole system where rather than
humans compete against humans using
better technology to exploit nature
its nature gives rise to humans humans
gives rise to technology so to be
sustainable technology has to
in turn be in service to the resilience
of nature
and this is i mean this is why i'm happy
to be here talking with you and i think
this is the core of your work and why
you have started with narrative in
memphis
there have to be people that are
oriented to a model of what
healthy civilization could even mean in
the presence of the kinds of things we
face
to be working towards building things
that
make such a possibility come about
within the increased adaptiveness of
that new system becomes the strange
attractor
yeah what you're saying is is so so
closely congruent to
the things i've been saying for years um
with totally different language
i speak for example of a transition
from a relationship of mother earth to a
relationship of lover earth
where we no longer just uh are
feel at liberty to take and take and
take as best we can
which is the proper relationship of a
child to a parent
um but where we understand that we
are here to give and take in
in harmonious measure and perhaps to
as with a lover to co-create something
together
so that really does translate into
abandoning the behavior of an apex
predator and taking responsibility
for the effects of our actions on the
other
it also means a reconception of who we
are
in relationship to the other in
relationship to nature
it's a change that goes all the way to
the bottom yeah
all the way to what we believe we are
what we believe reality is and the
relationship between us and reality
because what we understand to be
real is going to inform what we
understand to be meaningful
that is the basis for then what we are
making choices in service to
right um yeah i see it as
really an initiation into a different
collective state of being that also then
induces a different personal state of
being
because one hallmark of an initiation
is that you're faced with circumstances
that none of your existing tools are
sufficient
to handle right and you're you're then
forced or ever be strongly invited
to uh uh metamorphosize you know
grow and just to become something else i
mean i'm not going to say that it's
entirely new i think that at each stage
of human evolution
like with the advent of stone tools with
the advent of fire with the advent of
domestication and so on
like each of these qualitative
step ups in the our ability to
out-compete the rest of nature there was
at each point the possibility of coming
into a responsible
equilibrium that
necessitated taking some responsibility
and exercising some kind of restraint
so there are hunter-gatherer cultures
who and maybe some just still to this
day
who really understood themselves as
among other things as
stewards of the land and caretakers of
the land
among some of the native americans for
example the idea of the wild
was a repulsive concept
like no it's not the wild we're here
we're here to interact
it wasn't that they left no trace it was
that they
interacted in a positive way and left a
positive trace
and there were those at each stage of
our technological development that
didn't take responsibility and did
tremendous damage
so just to say that it's not an entirely
a new thing
that we're seeking here there are
precedents for it that operated
on um earlier levels of technological
development you know if you can look at
technology it's kind of
a step up function where you had a
sudden leap and then maybe a gradual
increase then another sudden leap and so
forth
you know there so there were stone age
cultures that
lived in equilibrium there were agrarian
cultures
that lived in equilibrium equilibrium
and maintained
ecological symbiosis for thousands of
years
and i'm not sure if we could say the
same for industrial
societies let alone digital societies
but just saying that there are
precedents
and cultural memories that we might be
able to draw on
as we forge a story that locates us
in a different relationship to nature
yeah i think i think it's interesting
because we're definitely not going
backwards right we're
moving to a society that is both higher
touch and higher nature as well as
higher tech
but a fundamentally different way of
thinking about what
technology is and what it's for
what it's for um
and so any orientation to say it was
good before let's go back we'll just
lose
but there's a lot of principles that
we've had in various previous phases
that are actually a critical part of it
and so you know one one thing
to what you said is that of course there
is a distribution of cultures that were
say
more harmonious with their environment
versus more exploitive
uh less warring versus more worrying and
in general the way the curve goes is
that the more warring culture is killed
the less boring cultures at a certain
point
and the ones that exploited the
environments have been ended up
taking over the ones that didn't at a
certain point and so
we can see that it's like
the only cultures that were kind of that
were more
peaceful that were left for a while was
if they didn't have natural resource
they weren't a threat they were in some
far away place like tibet
until tibet actually became a threat
because you know things like
modern media where its message could
damage the message
of china to the rest of the world and
then it had to be taken out and we could
see that with patriarchal versus
matriarchal cultures and
you know greece falling to rome and all
those types of things
and yet so what we're looking at is in
those phases
doing the more power dominant thing
won not doing it lost by default
and so the power dominant thing both
worked
and was compulsory right
now the power dominant thing has got to
a high enough level of power
that increasing the level of power on
all sides is actually what is breaking
the underlying substrate itself
and so it no longer can keep winning the
thing that has won so far the winning
in win lose itself is now the underlying
threat to survival
and so when you say we need new tools we
actually need new meta tools we need a
meta process by which we aren't trying
to create a situation that selects for
us
against others because that againstness
itself will actually break the ability
to even select for us
and so of course there have been lots of
epochs with the agricultural revolution
industrial revolution and there were
major changes
but i would say the epoch that we are on
the brink of that we're talking about
now
is like maybe the last time that
something
of this magnitude happened was homo
habilis and tool making
because you know we said like okay
you've got evolution it's a very old
process depending
on how we want to define it billions of
years on this earth or as old as the
universe
and that's a mathematical process that
just kept happening for a very long time
until tool making created a conscious
central serial rather than unconscious
decentral
parallel creative process and then there
have been a lot of
epochal shifts in how we do the tool
making thing
but we're really looking at a new third
creative process that is neither
evolution
nor tool making it's something that
navigates the relationship between the
both of them
it's a conscious right creation of holes
rather than an unconscious creation of
holes or consecration of parts
so i would say that that's kind of a
meta epoch
that we have not had a transition like
that
in the history of our species
that's very that's very interesting i
agree with that i think that
um what we face is qualitatively
different
than any of the technological
revolutions before
it's bigger than the neolithic
revolution it's bigger than the
industrial revolution
because all of those were an
intensification of
something that was already in progress
right it was a
next level of the development of the
technologies of control
and this is something entirely different
it's
a bigger and deeper qualitatively
different kind of revolution than
anything
that we've had before but every religion
spoke to it or
in the most part most religions spoke to
something like this with the what is
happening at the end of the mayan
calendar or the end of kali yuga and the
emergence of satyuga in
the hindu system or the you know the end
of
the end of times and purgatory and then
heaven or hell if we take these kind of
metaphorically we say
let's just play with the idea that the
rapture story in christianity was just
kind of like patient people looking and
saying hey
as we went from stone tools to metal
tools
and as we keep developing better and
better tools
we're destroying environments faster
than we were there are deserts where
there didn't used to be and the wars are
getting bigger
and they can just imagine that that
doesn't get to go on forever
at a certain point we become too
powerful to keep being that dumb
and so there's a story that says this
phase that we're in comes to an end
we fell out of the garden in terms of
how to live in harmony with things
this phase comes to an end there's a
purgatory where there's some really hard
reckoning with the choices we've made
and we either go a very different
direction where we kind of are
reintroduced to the garden but at a
higher order
or it or it's pretty bleak yeah i think
that's actually a literally true story
and we're just in purgatory now
we're actually in that eminent place
where
the choices we've been making have to be
not not only do we have to shift them we
actually have to make amends we have to
do reparations on those
choices which is how do we actually
clean the oceans not just polluting them
and fix the topsoil and
those types of things and so i think it
is like you know people can get
despairing or overwhelmed they could
also be like this is the most
interesting possible time to get to
contribute to a deeper level shift
of how for the future of all life
than anyone has ever had the opportunity
to contribute to and to just be like
even if i don't know how to do it i'm
going to
commit to do it before i know how and
start increasing
my understanding and sense making so i
can
more and more deeply engage right we may
not know the answers but at least
maybe we know the question you know we
know the
the direction we want to go and i think
you just named it it is
as reparations you know regeneration
healing
um what i mean this is the question i i
ask you know knowing that
no species on earth is given superfluous
or unnecessary gifts
that don't contribute to the well-being
and evolution of the whole
um the question is well what are our
gifts for
and maybe for the next 500 years they're
for healing the damage that's been done
after that they're probably for
something else that is
unimaginable and and who knows you know
why
why we're really here why we really have
this ability to
to forge exponential technology to enact
this new kind of evolution
who knows why but for the next few
centuries i think it's pretty clear
what we're here for and uh for the time
being that's good enough for me
yep agreed so i think like we have um
we got to a point this is like maybe a
good stopping point
you've really laid the foundation of
here's what needs to happen
here's the question to ask you know we
can do this again and
talk about more of of the how
i'll say one brief thing on the how-to
just so that those who are really paying
attention can be thinking about it
if the paperclip maximizer that we
currently have is a
collective intelligence system that is
working on humans as
the processors um predisposing them in
particular ways etc
but it is a collective intelligence
system that is oriented in a particular
way and getting better
the answer is a new collective
intelligence system
that is oriented in a different
direction that is actually in service to
evolution itself
increasing orderly complexity rather
than paper clip maximizing
and yet that also has the ability to
not just move in a direction but
increase its intelligence and compa
and capacity move in that direction so
we want to be thinking about how could
we have a fundamentally different kind
of collective intelligence which is not
just individual intelligence how do we
have humans interacting
with each other in ways that produces
system disposition that orients itself
in the evolutionary direction and
increases its capacity to do that and
yes maybe we can have a future
conversation where we dive into that
more but if people are thinking on it
that's a good area to be thinking in
yeah it would have a system component
and a story component
or a psychology component because
the system creates the individual an
individual creates the system
you know and like like you can try to
hold a story of
inter-being you know is the word i'd
like to use for it but we live in a
system that
every day in a million ways enforces
separation
so it's really hard to live from inter
being
and we could have a system that invites
us and supports us in being
cooperative and transparent and so forth
so we can work on many many levels i
think the systems level and the
individual level and that to me points
to a
convergence of activism and spirituality
right and i would say for people who
want to figure out okay well how do how
do i take these very macro topics and
apply them to myself in the near term if
i really care and i'm earnest and i say
okay well there is a collective
intelligence that is actually
predisposing even my action
facebook is moving me in a particular
direction capitalism and
state and etc actually have an influence
on me
i want to evolve to where i can actually
be part of an influence on the whole
that is in a different direction
but in order to increase my ability to
influence the whole in a positive
direction
i also need to decrease the way the
current system is influencing me
and have things around me that are
influencing me in a direction that i
want so how do i create
collective intelligence that i'm a part
of that is continuing to
uh support my own sovereignty and
sense-making and orient me in the right
direction
and i would say the degree to which you
can
find people that are also really
earnestly exploring these topics
and not ones that all agree with you but
are earnestly exploring them
and you can create higher quality
conversations with more regularity where
the space that you are in
is a space of earnest high quality
exploration across a diversity of points
of view
you will be moved in the right direction
better than if you leave
the input to your brain largely to those
who are doing broadcast
media continuously trying to control the
input to your brain
yeah that's uh very
attractive advice for me
validates the direction i've been going
of course i could just be rebelling
against my father or something
and rejecting the information that's
that's being fed to me by the structures
of power but
if so so be it
hey i want to say um briefly people who
are interested in this dialogue
you know um you're charles mentioned
lewis mumford and i'm sure he has
a list on the site of recommended
reading
things that we've talked about today you
know there's
i didn't come up with in really any of
the ideas that i'm saying i
at most are kind of kind of synthesizing
them but their ideas coming from bucky
fuller and
barber marks hubbard and krishnamurti
and david bohm and
and others that are worth looking at and
specifically some of the
some of the structures regarding
evolution as a creative process and then
technology as a
creative process and that making an
unstable oscillator and what the new
process will be and uh the distinctions
between
power and strength and have come largely
that a lot of brilliant structures have
come
through a collaboration with a a
friend of mine named forrest landry and
he goes into those
structures in a lot more formal detail
in some of his writing so i'd encourage
anyone who's interested to look that up
and um just a
you know a little bit on resources and
yeah
if people are interested and questions
come in and we get to do a future
dialogue to explore those further that
would be really fun
and you said you had a blog or something
like that and you have a podcast as well
yeah civilizationemerging.com is a blog
that i have and there's a podcast called
collective insights and there's a couple
different show hosts there's a
really brilliant doctor who does a lot
on the future of medicine named dr
heather sanderson and then i do some on
these kind of social topics
which will include one posting soon
where charles was there sharing about
climate change and polarization and
the really fun conversation great okay
yeah we'll put links to those
in our blurb for this show yeah yeah
all right well great daniel thank you so
much for uh taking all this time
likewise thanks for having me charles
and thank you for
all the work that you are doing in
helping people
shift narrative and sense making and i
look forward to
continue collaboration all right
this has been a new and ancient story
with your host charles eisenstein
i offer this podcast in the spirit of
the gift by which i mean
that i don't withhold premium content
for a price or put up paywalls or do
affiliate marketing
or have advertising or anything like
that instead i rely on supporters
like you if you would like to support it
you can subscribe
at charles eisenstein.net for a small
monthly amount or you can subscribe for
free as well
either way you get the same content
everything's the same
and you'll be notified every time a new
podcast comes out
also on the site you can find archived
episodes
along with everything else that i
produce essays books
videos online courses thank you very
much for listening
and i'll be with you again next time
you